Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf is yud bet יב,
Yud Bet, we pick up at the bottom of yud aleph amud
bet יא עמוד ב Yud Aleph Amud Bet and we are getting
we are continuing with this discussion about
dividing a courtyard and then based on the number of doors that
you had and then there was a question about well based on
the number of, yeah, lefi ptacheha לפי פתחיה. Lefi Ptacheha. Anyway, each
door gets anyway some space before it, it's divided according to the
inhabitants but each doorway gets some space before it. Anyway and then
the it brought in a baraita zo ברייתא זו Baraita Zo which
shifted from dividing a chatzer חצר, Chatzer, a courtyard, to the issue
of a mavoy מבוי Mavoy or a mavoy מבוי, Mavoy, I should
say. Thank you, mavoy מבוי. Mavoy. Anyway and the question about, you
know, questions about different courtyards that open up into the mavoy מבוי
Mavoy and whether the back one has rights to its own space
which basically decided was not. And then there was we're going to
go on now to other parts of that baraita ברייתא. Baraita. So
five lines from the bottom. Amar Mar אמר מר: Amar Mar: Im
haya satum uvikesh liftocho אם היה סתום וביקש לפותחו. Im Haya Satum
Uvikesh Liftocho. So basically somebody had their back door was let's say
opening up into another mavoy מבוי Mavoy back here and they wanted
to now open up his door
after it
being sealed. Ain bnei mavoy
me’akvin alav אין בני מבוי מעכבין עליו. Ain Bnei Mavoy Me’akvin Alav.
Then they can't stop him. Amar
Rava אמר רבא: Amar Rava: Lo shanu ela shelo paratz ptzimav לא
שנו אלא שלא
פרץ פצימיו. Lo Shanu Ela Shelo Paratz Ptzimav. That is only true
if the sort of like doorframe has not been destroyed. Imagine that
you close a door and you put like, you know, sometimes you
see they put like a big, not piece of like wood, you
know, to fill up the hole of the door, fine, but that's
not paratz ptzimav פרץ פצימיו Paratz Ptzimav because you still have the
opportunity to take down the wood and open the door. But let's
say you actually destroy, you fill it with bricks and destroy the
doorframe, okay, so in that case then you've made it clear that
it stops being a door, you're giving up any right to continue
to use that as a door and in that case bnei mavoy
me’akvin alav בני מבוי מעכבין עליו, Bnei Mavoy Me’akvin Alav, they can
stop you. Amar lei Abaye le-Rava אמר ליה אביי לרבא: Amar Lei
Abaye Le-Rava: Tanya demisayei lach תניא דמסייע לך. Tanya Demisayei Lach. He
has a baraita ברייתא Baraita that supports you. Bayit satum, yesh lo
arba amot בית סתום יש לו ארבע אמות. Bayit Satum, Yesh Lo
Arba Amot. Paratz ptzimav, ein lo arba amot פרץ פצימיו אין לו
ארבע אמות. Paratz Ptzimav, Ein Lo Arba Amot. So if you have
a remember we were just this was the whole thing that if
you have a house that opens up into a courtyard so for
every door that opens into that courtyard, if you're going to divide
the courtyard you get four amot אמות Amot in front of the
door. Okay now what if the door has been sealed up? So
if the house has been sealed up, so if you have destroyed
the doorframe you don't have your four amot אמות. Amot. If you
did not destroy the doorframe then you do have the four amot
אמות, Amot, then it's considered like a still a potentially functional door.
That's actually even a bigger chidush חידוש Chidush because that's not only
retaining a right to reopen it, that's actually seeing it currently as
an active door even while it's still sealed, so I think that's
even a bigger chidush חידוש Chidush than what we're talking about. Okay
now we'll skip the parenthesis. Bayit satum בית סתום Bayit Satum similarly
eino metamei kol svivav אינו מטמא כל סביביו. Eino Metamei Kol Svivav.
You have a dead body in a house, okay, and and you
close the door but you did not maybe even you sealed the
door but you did not destroy the doorframe. So the halacha הלכה
Halacha here is that there's like two halachot הלכות Halachot that are
relevant here and like Rashi רש"י Rashi and Tosafot תוספות Tosafot play
with both of them. One halacha הלכה Halacha is the idea of
a kever קבר. Kever. You know Chazal חז"ל Chazal said that once
something is defined as an actual grave, as an actual coffin,
then it is metamei מטמא Metamei not only when you're on top
or below it which is what a normal dead body would be,
but even if you were to touch the side, touch the sides
of a coffin.
And there's a little discussion in Rashi רש"י Rashi Tosafot תוספות Tosafot
but under some circumstances you also can't be within four amot ארבע
אמות Arba Amot of the grave. You know we always say that
if you're within four amot ארבע אמות Arba Amot of the grave
it causes you're tamei טמא Tamei and that's the way to keep
Kohanim כוהנים Kohanim at a safe distance. So is this house considered
like a coffin? You have a dead body in it, all the
doors are sealed up, is it considered like a coffin?
Okay, and the windows are closed whatever. There's another halacha הלכה Halacha
called sof tumah latzet סוף טומאה לצאת Sof Tumah Latzet which I'm
not going to get into which sort of Tosafot תוספות Tosafot also
plays with as well. Anyway, so it does not make everything around
it tamei טמא, Tamei, it is not considered like it is totally
sealed. You imagine that a door will be opened and the body
will be taken out and so it doesn't have a status of
a coffin. Paratz ptzimav פרץ פצימיו Paratz Ptzimav but once you destroy
the whole frame then metamei kol svivav מטמא כל סביביו, Metamei Kol
Svivav, it is like coffin and all around it becomes tamei טמא.
Tamei. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbah Bar Bar Chana Amar Rabbi
Yochanan: Mevoot hamefulashot le-ir acheret uvikshu bnei ha-ir lesotmam bnei oto מבואות
המפולשות לעיר אחרת וביקשו בני העיר לסותמם בני אותו. Mevoot Hamefulashot Le-ir
Acheret Uvikshu Bnei Ha-ir Lesotmam Bnei Oto. בני אותה העיר מעכבין עליהן.
b'nei osah ha'ir meakvin aleihen. So this is very interesting, right? You've
got basically, okay,
here you've got what happened to my nice black marker?
Anyway, מפולש mefulash means it's open. So a normal מבוי סתום, mavoi
satum, hence the name, right, that's like a private alley and and
that, you know, that's your private alley into your that your courtyards
open up to. A מבוי מפולש mavoi mefulash is pretty much like
a רשות הרבים reshus harabim or not exactly maybe, because a because
רשות הרבים reshus harabim maybe doesn't have courtyards empty to open directly
into it. Oft what you'll have here is if you want to
see the whole sort of, I mean it's not always like this,
but imagine, right, okay, like
the side streets as it were, right? This is
this is your רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. These are you go into
these, you know, these מבואות סתומים, mavo'os satumim, right, which have in
them individual חצרות, chatzeiros, right, so like you go into a street,
like a dead end street, okay, from your רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
right, that dead end street you can go into like almost like
a court, you know. So these are courts, right, but you know,
we have we have courts sometimes, they still have them, you know,
couple of houses around, a little, whatever, okay, so these are your
courts and this is your dead end street and that's your רשות
הרבים, reshus harabim, okay. So that's basically the configuration. Okay, but you
could have that this is a מבוי מפולש, mavoi mefulash, right, and
enters into another רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, okay.
All right, so let's say you've got a מבוי מפולש. mavoi mefulash.
Now, this says now what's a little confusing to me is is
that it's going to another town, okay. So, so anyway, you have
a town here, okay, maybe you've got I don't exactly get the
idea of town, I'm not really getting this, but it doesn't matter,
the basic point is the same. You've got a מבוי mavoi here
that goes from town A to town B, okay, a מבוי. mavoi.
Yes, not a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim.
Yeah, whatever, I yeah, so I don't really get it. I mean,
I'm wondering if more it's calling a town something a little bit
more local. Like a neighborhood. Yeah, my I think it must mean
a neighborhood, but let's not even worry about that right now. Okay,
anyway, here you've got your מבוי, mavoi, okay, and it gets you
into from one city to the next. So, I don't know, do
they have better pictures there that make it more comprehensive? Or do
they basically re-interpret town more like neighborhood?
They actually translate as city.
Yeah, well city is a wrong translation. An עיר ir is a
is a town, okay. כרך kerach is a city, כפר kfar is
a village.
Okay, so anyway, they also say city.
Well, whatever, that's even harder to understand. Anyway, let's keep on going.
Okay, now, ומבואות המפולשות לעיר אחרת, umvo'os hamfulashos l'ir acheres, וביקשו בני
העיר לסותמם. ubikshu b'nei ha'ir lsotmam.
Now basically, here's the story, okay. So, the מבוי mavoi started here.
All right, this is sort of the locus of the מבוי mavoi
and somehow it gets you access to that city. It's not a
מבוי mavoi in that city. It's sort of seen as local here.
So anyway, what you want to do is say this is my
private street, I'm just going to close it off right like this,
okay. It's our private street, why not? At least even certainly here
it's still private. I don't know what the story is in this
other space. Okay, so can we just close it off? It's our
own private street. Okay, so it says בני אותה העיר מעכבין עליהן.
b'nei osah ha'ir meakvin aleihen. No, you can't, because you have now
made this city lose its or this town lose, it had been
used to having this type of access into into town A and
you've basically closed off its access. So even though on one hand
it's your private street, it's a private street that you had that
that in practice has been used by the רבים rabim and has
given them, you know, a certain type of a of an access,
and you cannot take that away from them.
Yes, an easement.
Well, I guess, I mean, if just imagine, I mean, this picture's
a little confusing because I mean because I have I'm it's a
little not clear to me, I mean this I understand, but imagine
you just have a private street, right, that has been now, you
know, sometimes with private streets they have gates in front of it,
they don't let regular traffic go through it for all those reasons.
You also right, but let's say you had something that was a
private street, but it had become the practice to be used as
a regular way to get through, to cut through, you know, from
one place to the next, and the people and the people had
not put gates and had not limited the access, okay. So it
had been established as that as the public was using that. And
now you decided you wanted to reassert your rights and you wanted
to seal that off. That's the case. Okay, so we don't exactly
have to worry about the עיר ir or whatever, the point is
you wanted to reassert your rights to your private street and to
stop the public. So the הלכה halacha is, okay, you can't, I'm
sorry, וביקשו בני אותה העיר מעכבין עליהן. b'nei osah ha'ir meakvin aleihen.
לא מיבעיא היכא דליכא דרכא אחריתא דמעכבי, lo mibaya heicha d'leika darcha
achrita d'meakvi, it goes without saying that if this is the only
way of accessing the other location, of course you can't close off.
access by by reasserting your rights to your private street, אלא אפילו
כי איכא דרכא אחרינא נמי מעכב *ela afilu ki ika darcha achrina
nami m'akev*, even if they have another way to get into your
town, you can't close it off.
You have another road?
Thank you. Because משום *mishum*, derive משום דרב יהודה אמר Amar, רב
*mishum d'Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, because Rav Yehuda said in the name
of Rav, דאמר מצר metzar שהחזיקו בו רבים אסור לקלקלו *d'amar meizar
she'hecheziku vo rabim asur l'kalkelo*. If you have a path that the
רבים *rabim* have taken possession of, you know it's they, I won't
say right of eminent domain, but you know, asserted their use of
and whatever, then it becomes they they you cannot take that right
away from them. Okay, you cannot destroy it. Okay. And by the
way, if you look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, מצר שהחזיקו בו רבים
אסור לקלקלו *meizar she'hecheziku vo rabim asur l'kalkelo*, תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* says,
היינו כשהחזיקו ברשות *hainu k'she'hecheziku birshut*. ברשות *Birshut*, excuse me. They were
they had permission initially. They weren't violating, you know, you weren't screaming
and yelling and saying, don't use my private street and they were
just using it anyway. Initially you allowed them to and then they
had established their right. אבל אם באו להחזיק שלא ברשות *Aval im
bau l'hachzik shelo birshut*, יש למחות בידם ולנקוט פזרא וליתיב *yesh limchot
b'yadam u'linkot pizra v'leisiv*, כמו שמוכח בבבא קמא *k'mo she'muchach b'Bava Kama*.
Remember, you know, if they're trying to to use your street and
you don't want them to, you can go ahead and take a
hoe and bang them in the head if they try to get
in. That was the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* in בבא קמא *Bava Kama*.
Okay? לנקוט פזרא וליתיב *Linkot pizra v'leisiv*. Yeah, exactly. So basically, if,
though, you allowed them and they took this and they and they
took this with permission and they established this presence, you cannot cut
them off. I gotta tell you, I wasn't thinking about this when
I was listening to it yesterday, but I was driving and I
was listening to NPR and they were doing a piece about, I'm
already missing I'm already getting the exact point, but it was about
how, you know, with the social media, you know, for a lot
of companies it's a key part of their access to their customers
and whatever through Facebook. I wasn't getting the specifics, but basically it
was, and then what happens if somebody comes along and like defriends
you and effectively I wish I remembered the specifics, but effectively it's
you know, you know they've now cut off your access to all
of these customers. And the example they gave was, it's like, I
mean just shocking, the example they gave was it says, it's like,
you know, everybody has like used these public, you know, these streets
and that technically are private and that you know established, and then
somebody comes and re-establish, you know, and reasserts their private ownership and
cuts off all your access. So anyway, it was really interesting. It
was exactly this case applied to the virtual world. I'll try to
find the piece in NPR. Yeah, but it's a different type of
a חזקה *chazaka*. It's like a חזקת שימוש *chazkat shimush*, right? A
normal חזקה *chazaka* comes with a claim that you purchased it, remember?
This is a type of a חזקה *chazaka*. This is an interesting
contrast because before when we had, hey look, I've been using your
wall and you haven't complained, right, he said that's not enough, I
have to say I bought the rights to use your wall. Here
the רבים *rabim* does not have to say they bought the rights.
In the case of the רבים *rabim*, and that's a very good
contrast, the fact that they were using it without complaint and had
established their presence. I don't know how long it takes to establish
their presence. That that gives them rights. That can't be now just
taken away. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay.
אמר Amar,
רב עננא *Amar Rav Anana*. So now we're going to continue with
this theme a little bit. אמר רב עננא אמר שמואל *Amar Rav
Anana amar Shmuel*, מבואות המפולשים לרשות הרבים *mevo'ot ha'mefulashim l'reshut ha'rabim*. Okay,
that's an easier explanation. Okay, they go from one רשות הרבים *reshut
ha'rabim* to the other. מפולשים לרשות הרבים *Mefulashim l'reshut ha'rabim*. ובקשו בני
מבואות להעמיד להם דלתות
*u'vikshu b'nei mevo'ot l'ha'amid lahem dlatot*. Same idea. You have your private
private alleyway, but it cuts into the רשות הרבים *reshut ha'rabim*. And
now you want to, what you want to do is, fine, you
want to use our מבוי *mavoi*, be our guest. But we are
not so happy, right, because everybody is sort of going you know
whatever. So what we want to, wait let me check I got
this right, ובקשו בני המבואות *u'vikshu b'nei ha'mevo'ot*. Oh no, okay, I'm
sorry. So it's not doors in front of the חצר *chatzer*, it's
doors in front of the מבוי *mavoi*. We just want to do
this.
There's actually a drawing in that.
Of doors in front of the מבוי *mavoi* like this. Okay, you
just say, look, you know, you're using your רשות הרבים *reshut ha'rabim*,
you have not established, apparently I mean it would make sense you
want to shortcut, but we're not saying that the רבים *rabim* go
through here. You've not established right as using this as a thoroughfare.
This is still private and we want to stop we want to
make sure that the רבים *rabim* don't start, you know, getting in
here and when there's a lot of people in the street they
don't start, you know, coming into our מבוי *mavoi*. We want to
protect our private space.
They can open the door whenever they want?
Yeah, you want to knock on the door, you want to come
in, be my guest.
The רבים *rabim* can't open it.
I don't know about that. But the point is it's still less
of a just open invitation as if there wasn't a door. Okay?
So בני רשות הרבים מעכבין עליו *b'nei reshut ha'rabim m'akevin alav*. Nope,
the בני רשות הרבים *b'nei reshut ha'rabim* say sorry you're not allowed
to do that. Why not? סברי מינה הני מילי בארבע אמות *Savri
minah hani mili b'arba amot* כדרבי זירא אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav
Nachman, *k'de'Rabbi Zeira amar Rav Nachman*. דאמר רבי זירא אמר רב נחמן
ארבע אמות הסמוכות לרשות הרבים כרשות הרבים דמיין *D'amar Rabbi Zeira amar
Rav Nachman arba amot ha'smuchot l'reshut ha'rabim k'reshut ha'rabim damyan*. Because we
thought that maybe the רשות הרבים *reshut ha'rabim* automatically gets essentially a
sidewalk. That's, you know, you have the רשות הרבים *reshut ha'rabim*, although
again this was not for cars, this was for people with their
horses and buggies and whatever, but nevertheless, even though this is the
street and that's clearly identified, you know, maybe it's paved or it's
got a curb or whatever, you get the ארבע אמות *arba amot*
at the edges, essentially some type of a buffer or a sidewalk.
Okay? So that ארבע אמות *arba amot* would go ארבע אמות *arba
amot* into your מבוי *mavoi*. And therefore if you're making a door
you're cutting us off from our
Right, so the
נפקא מינא *nafka mina* would be that if that were the issue
you'd be allowed to make the door as long as you did
it within four אמות *amos* in. So we thought that was the
whole reason, was just the four אמות *amos*. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says,
where were we?
Okay, by the way, רש"י *Rashi* points out that the נפקא מינא
*nafka mina* of this הלכה halakhic *halacha* is not just property rights,
but there's a הלכה halakha *halacha* about ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים מטהר
*safek tumah bi'reshut harabim metaher*. So let's say you had a ספק
*safek* about whether something was טמא *tamei* and was within the four
אמות *amos* or you know over the edge of רשות הרבים *reshut
harabim*. So he's saying that would still be considered רשות הרבים *reshut
harabim*. But it's also presumably property rights. So the question is, hold
on, so we thought it was that issue, and then if you
made the door within four אמות *amos*, after four אמות *amos*, you'd
be okay. לא היא *lo hi*, that's not true. התם ענין טומאה
*hatam inyan tumah*, that's a טומאה *tumah* הלכה halakha, *halacha*, it wasn't
רש"י *Rashi*, it was the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אבל הכא זימנין דדחקי
בני רשות הרבים דעיילי טובי *aval hacha zimnin d'daichei benei reshut harabim
d'aili tuvei*. Here, sometimes even if they're not using this as a
thoroughfare, if the רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* is crowded—again, you have to
remember that sometimes רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* is more of a marketplace
than it is necessarily of a thoroughfare. Okay, if the or whatever,
it doesn't matter, if the רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* is crowded, sometimes
they'll, you know, spill over into here. And now, of course you
could say how far in do they go? But it's interesting what
it's saying is this idea that the רבים *rabbim* has established through
use their rights which now cannot be taken away if you didn't
object initially. If you objected initially and never let it happen, געזונטהייט
*gezunteheit*. But if you didn't object initially and let it happen, they've
established it. It's not just their rights to use it as a
thoroughfare, just rights to use it as spillover space. That's also a
type of a right. And now you can't take that away, you
know.
They can't get in there though.
What? Open a door, right? No, it doesn't work the same way.
You know, everybody's crowding and elbowing one another and you've got a
door in front of you. You're not going to knock at the
door with all the crowd or whatever, but you would easily just
spill in there. Okay, so that also is a type of a
right. Yes, David, you had a question.
Is he suggesting it's only open at one end?
It's not because they're using it for a shortcut. Right, I know,
I said they're not using it as a shortcut. I mean, it's
still said מפולש *mifulash*, but it could be just מפולש לרשות הרבים
*mifulash l'reshut harabim*, not מפולש *mifulash* at both ends. Right, I said
that. They're not using it as a shortcut. Okay, I didn't draw
it that way, but I said that. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So you can still put the door. The upshot of this סוגיא
*sugya* is you can
still put the door inward. Yeah, I mean, if you put the
door inward to a point where it would never be overspill, then
presumably that would be totally fine. But would that be four אמות
*amos*? What? No, not four אמות *amos*. The point is the overspill
is much more, it could be more than four אמות *amos*. But
if it's like if it's if they haven't established use within twenty
אמות *amos* inside, you could put it within twenty אמות *amos* inside.
Does he say anything about the shortcut or?
No, no, if they had used it as a shortcut, then there
would be an obvious point. Okay, let's go on. Okay. ולא *V'lo*
says that דעד דאית ביה תשעה קבין לזה ותשעה קבין לזה *d'ad
d'it bei tisha kavim l'zeh v'tisha kavim l'zeh*. You cannot force a
division of a field until each person gets תשעה קבין *tisha kavim*.
I still didn't look up what exactly that translates to, I don't
know if one of you has something. Let me see if I
can quickly find find that, I'm sorry. The Steinsaltz did find—did tell
you what that was? I should have—I should have done that. What?
To this קב kab, *kav*. Yeah, in the—nine
קב kab. *kav* is between 950 and 1400 square meters.
Square meters. And a meter is about a yard. Okay. Yeah, so
a yard—so let's say a yard is somewhere between 100 and 150
square—a קב *kav* is between 100 and 150 square yards or square
meters. Okay, does that give you an image? Again? Well, right, football
field. Wait a minute, a football field is 100 yards. Right, 100
yards, right, but 100 yards by 1 yard is 100 square yards.
Right? Yeah, 10 yards by 10 yards.
So let's go—so it's actually not that large of an area.
Right, it's like it would be like the length of a football
field and like nine yards in the other direction. 30 oh. No,
I said and nine yards in the other direction.
Oh, look skinny.
But if you want to do square anyway, fine. Okay. All right,
we'll call it 100 square yards or 100 square meters. Fine. So
nine would be 900 square meters.
All right,
so... ותשעה קבין לזה *v'tisha kavim l'zeh*. ולא פליגי מר כי אתרא
ומר כי אתרא *v'lo peligi mar ki atra u'mar ki atra*, each
one according to his own location. Okay, which basically tells us, says,
means that if you have a very rich soil, then it's meaningful
to have a smaller plot of land. But if you don't have
rich soil, obviously it's not considered that I have anything substantial until
I have a larger plot of land. ובבל על מאי *v'vavel al
mai*, what's the story in בבל *Bavel*? אמר רב יוסף Rav Yosef
בי רדיא יומא *Amar Rav Yosef bei radya yoma*, the amount of
space that it takes to plow it in a day. Okay, one
day's worth of plowing. So now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, מאי
בי רדיא יומא *mai bei radya yoma*? How do you how do
you translate—meaning not what does the words mean, but how do you
how do you— How do you how do you compute that? אי
יומא זרעא Ei yoma zara, תרי יומי כרבא. So the way רש״י
Rashi explains it is is that if you're talking about like the
time it takes to plow when you're doing the seeding, okay, apparently
you would plow it, you know, early, and then you would sort
of as, you know, earlier on in the in the season, when
the ground was harder, and then you'd plow it and you'd soften
it up, and then you'd plow it again at the time of
the season. So it went quicker, the plowing at the time of
the seeding. Okay, so if you mean אי יומא זרעא, so time
one day's worth of plowing at the time of seeding, okay, so
that would be תרי יומי כרבא לא הוי. Trei yomei karva lo
havei. That would not equal two days of plowing at the earlier
stage, at the plowing time, meaning the time when it had been
unplowed beforehand, before the seeding time. Now, big deal. I mean, who
cares that it doesn't equal two days? So what? It's one day's
worth of plowing at this time. So what רש״י Rashi says the
problem is is that you can't hire anybody to work for a
day and a half. Okay, so it's basically saying for such a
small place you're going to be stuck either way. If if it's
if it's the size that it's one day's of plowing at the
seeding time, you'll be able to hire people at the seeding season,
but you won't be able to hire people at the plowing season
because who's gonna want to get hired for a day and a
half? אי יומא כרבא, Ei yoma karva, if it's a day's worth
of plowing at the plowing season, so יומא דזרעא לא הוי. Yoma
dezara lo havei. That won't even be a full day worth of...
wait a minute, does that make sense? Yeah, yeah, it won't because
it goes a lot faster at the at the seeding time. Then
you certainly won't be able to hire anybody at the seeding time.
Who's gonna want to get hired for less than a full day?
So איבעית אימא יומא דכרבא, Ibayit eima yoma dekarva, either I could
tell you it is a one day during the plowing season, okay,
דכרי ותני. Dekhari vetani. Now, and you do it and you do
it again. Now what does that mean? So there's a whole different
readings of רש״י. Rashi. Hold on, I'm trying to now remember how
רש״י Rashi read this this whole complication. Wait a
minute. Sorry, hold on. איבעית אימא יומא דכרבא ודכרי ותני ויומא דזרעא.
Ibayit eima yoma dekarva udekhari vetani veyoma dezara. Oh
yeah, so רש״י Rashi just right he read it as. It's one
day's worth of plowing in the plowing season and, comma, during the
seeding season, even though it's less than one day's worth of plowing,
דכרי ותני, Dekhari vetani, you'll just plow it twice, okay? So hire
a crew during the seeding season and it will make it into
a full day's work. Have them plow it twice, that'll be better
for the seeds anyway.
Okay, ואיבעית אימא יומא דזרעא, Veibayit eima yoma dezara, ואיבעית אימא יומא
דזרעא, veibayit eima yoma dezara, or I could say it's one day's
working during the seeding season. How about the problem that you won't
get a full day's work at the plowing season? So we're talking
about בהדורי. Bahadurei. It's a type of a rocky terrain and because
it's a rocky terrain, so one day's worth of plowing during the
seeding season will actually equal two days' worth of plowing during the
plowing season. All right, whatever. But the problem is that's all very
nice as a היכי תימצי. Heichi timtzei. The question is, what if
you don't have those particulars working out? But it doesn't but the
you get the point of the גמרא. Gemara The point of the
גמרא Gemara is, you know, you have to figure it in a
way that it's a reasonable plot of land that can actually, you
know, something that somebody would invest in for growing. So if the
way the specifics work out is that it's not worth the effort,
you know, to grow in it because of those details, then it
would not have a דין חלוקה. Din chaluka. Then you cannot force
a division. So that's really however those specifics work out, that's clearly
the point. You have to make sure that this is something that
is viable. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: דולא.
Davla. Let's say you've got a like a well that is used
for like a ditch or like what, not a ditch, let's call
it a
a canal that is used for irrigating the field. Okay, now apparently
this is something that is being shared and now they want to
split it. I must tell you I don't fully understand how do
you split a canal or a type of a, you know, of
water, like what do you do? You put a wall down the
middle of it or something? So it wasn't exactly clear. רש״י Rashi
even describes it as a well. Like the fact that we are
in partnership of it, fine, we take turns using it. But we're
talking about דין חלוקה, Din chaluka, forcing a split. So what does
a forcing of a split mean? Maybe it means that maybe it
means that until now we've been does it mean a physical split?
Does it mean that until now we've been just, you know, it's
shared and everybody uses it when they want to use it? And
we want to say, no, you know, you only get to use
it Monday, Wednesday, Friday, and I only get to use it Sunday,
Tuesday, Thursday. Right? Maybe so I wonder if that's also part of
this דין חלוקה Din chaluka idea. Dividing it not in terms of
physically, but dividing it in terms of time. Yes, what do you
want to say?
But you can divert the water.
Maybe, I'm not sure it's talking about that, but maybe. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so you've got this well,
דולא. Davla. So אמר רב נחמן, כדי דלויו יומא פרדיסא. Kedei diluyo
yoma pardesa. If you have enough to draw each day...
wait, pardesa is the next one. Pardesa regarding...
All right, I'm sorry, כדי דלויו יומא, Kedei diluyo yoma, thank you,
כדי דלויו יומא, Kedei diluyo yoma, thank you, כדי דלויו יומא. Kedei
diluyo yoma. If you have enough to draw each day. So the
way רש״י Rashi says, עד שיבא כדי להשקות שדה כדי פעולת יום
לזה וכדי פעולת יום לזה משום שכר פועל. Ad sheyavo kedei lehashkot
sadeh kedei peulat yom lazeh ukdei peulat yom lazeh mishum sechar poel.
So if basically so that sounds like you're actually physically splitting it.
So if there's enough... water left on my half that I can
sort of use it for a day’s work of work and this
is consistent with the idea I’ve got to hire workers, right, so
then it’s fine. Then I hire workers for the day and they'll
have it available for the day, that water. But if after the
split it only will provide enough water for for a half day,
that's not viable. Okay, I still don't get exactly how we're physically
splitting this, but I probably don't understand physically what we're talking about.
Okay.
Water's owned by whom?
Jointly. And now you want to force a split. Somehow we jointly
own this source of water. Okay? We want to physically split it
in a way that will allow me only access to half of
it at any time. Again, I don't understand physically what we're talking
about, but that's the reality. Can you force a split on me
if I don't want to? So if my half will provide me
enough water on a daily basis, a full day's worth of water,
the answer is yes, because then I can hire workers for the
day. But if it will not provide me a full day's worth
of water, then you cannot force a split. All right. Again, I
don't get it. Like after that day is over, does it get
replenished? I mean, I don't understand how it works. Okay, but let's
move on. Okay, we get the idea. פרדיסא. Pardisa. Now, you have
a orchard. אמר אביי דשמואל, Amar Abaye de'Shmuel, בר שלושה קבים. bar
shlosha kabim.
So this is not nine קב, this is three קב. Okay, so
300 meters, square meters, 300 square meters. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami
hachi, דהאומר לחבירו מנת בכרם אני מוכר לך. de'ha-omer l'chavero menat b'karem
ani mocher lach.
Somebody says to a friend, I'm going to sell you a portion
in my vineyard. So vineyard is a type of a פרדיסא, pardisa,
right, it's got like, you know, it's a פרדיס pardis is a
garden for trees and for and for grapes, etc., for for vines.
So סומכוס אומר לא יפחות מג' קבים. Sumchus omer lo yifchos mi-gimmel
kabim. So you didn't say how much. So you basically sold a,
wrote a document, I have sold you a portion, a plot, מנת
בכרם, menat b'karem, a plot in my vineyard. So how big is
a plot? Okay, so same idea, ג' קבים. gimmel kabim. The same
way if you split, that's the minimum you need to make something
viable, so also if somebody sells you a plot, we'll interpret it
as the minimum size to make it viable, ג' קבים. gimmel kabim.
Okay, so what? Sumchus says that, yeah. אמר רבי יוסי אין אלו
אלא דברי נביאות. Amar Rabbi Yosi ein elu ela divrei nevi'os. Oh,
those are words of prophecy. Which basically means like, I don't know
where you got that from. Okay, which תוספות Tosafot says, if you
were wondering, this is not a compliment. Okay, so if you take
a look at תוספות, Tosafot, אמר רבי יוסי אין אלו אלא דברי
נביאות לא לשבח קאמר. amar Rabbi Yosi ein elu ela divrei nevi'os
lo l'shabe'ach ka-amar. Oh my god, you just had a רוח הקודש
Ruach HaKodesh with that idea. No, that's not what he's saying. אלא
כלומר שאומר בלא טעם. Ela kelomar she-omer belo ta'am. You know, you're
just making this up. It's like no proof, no evidence, סתם, stam,
you know, okay, it's like it's like prophecy. It doesn't come from
any, that's not the endeavor of תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-ba'al peh.
Okay? תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh is proof, is text, is
logical argument. It's not just סתם stam saying stuff like, you know,
it's not רוח הקודש. Ruach HaKodesh. All right. Although it is interesting
sometimes when a פוסק posek wants to sort of say something like
I don't have any textual proof but here's like my gut instinct
about this, like what, you know, what I feel is right, he
has a word he calls מסברת הכרס אני אומר, nisvarat hakeres ani
omer, which is like from the logic of my stomach I say,
which basically means my gut instinct tells me. Okay. But anyway, so
wait. He could be wrong? He's not saying he's wrong. He's saying
how the heck do you know? Okay? I don't know what the
answer is, but
meaning you're right, but
I don't know meaning like I'm not saying you're right, I'm meaning
like, I don't know. Okay.
Rabbi says that, I have to listen to it.
All right, whatever. Anyway, אין אלו אלא דברי נביאות. Ein elu ela
divrei nevi'os. Okay, בבבל מאי? b'Bavel mai? Now what would be the
story in בבבל? Bavel? אמר רבא בר כסנא תלת אציאתא. Amar Rava
bar Kasna tlath atzi'ata. Three, three אציאתא. atzi'ata.
Now what's an אציאתא? atzi'ata? Three like units. And each unit is
בני תריסר גופני, b'nei tresar gufney, 12,
12 vines in a unit. So 12 vines and three of those
units, each one having 12 vines. Of course you could say also
here, you could say about all of this, אין אלו אלא דברי
נביאות. ein elu ela divrei nevi'os. Like why that claim was raised
exactly against that point? But maybe the point is like this. If
we're talking about the question of דין חלוקה, din chaluka, is this
something viable? So okay, we're going to look, we're going to assess
based on our knowledge about how the, how you know the ground
works, how the community works and so on, what is considered viable.
That's not דברי נביאות, divrei nevi'os, it's just an assessment based on
looking at the facts. The דברי נביאות divrei nevi'os was when I
wrote in my document I'm selling you a plot in my vineyard.
Okay, or so that, you know, a plot in my vineyard, that's
there's no parameters to that. So to say it means it means
the smallest plot possible that's viable the same as דין חלוקה, din
chaluka, no that's sort of the element of דברי נביאות. divrei nevi'os.
The rest of this is not דברי נביאות, divrei nevi'os, the rest
of this is just we have a criteria, what is a viable
thing, שמואל אמר, Shmuel amar, and we're going to assess whether the
facts fit that criteria. But the, the arbitrary sort of the term
in the in the document, that was דברי נביאות divrei nevi'os to
interpret what it means. Yes.
When you're forcing a division, that's like one party is just inflicting
it on the other. Right, like set to have a minimum that
you have to guarantee to the other party. Right, but if you're
selling, presumably the other party has some say in it and there's
going to be a dollar amount.
Right, well that's
also... amount of money paid and factoring that in and looking about
other circumstantial evidence. So that's probably where this דברי נביאות *divrei nevius*
challenge is coming from, like, you know, there's other things to be
looked at and you're not, you know, you're making it up out
of thin air. Yes.
Back to the first one, דופרא *dofra*, what does that, what's the
meaning of that? They translate here "cistern" but...
Yeah, like the דלי *dli* is a, like a bucket. So it's
like something you draw water from.
Yeah, that's kind of... in ancient Mesopotamia
the irrigation was by diverting rivers and...
rather than by... So maybe that's what it means. That here, that's
what... okay. All right, let's go back...
somewhat with wells... or rivers...
got it, got it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. So now because they had this phrase אין אלו אלא
דברי נביאות *ein elu ela divrei nevius*, we have a lovely opportunity
to have a little bit of a digression. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
So, okay, let's just read that. פותא דאתיא בני תריסר גופני כהאי
דריפקא בי יומא *Posa de'atya bnei treisar gupni keha'i derafika bei yoma*.
The amount of land and here it's telling you again this idea
of what's minimum viable. The amount of land that one person can
sort of like weed in a day. So a full day's worth
of work, that's the minimum for this case of dividing. אמר רב
אבדימי דמן חיפה *Amar Rav Avdimi demin Haifa*, מיום שחרב בית המקדש
ניטלה נבואה nevuah. מן הנביאים וניתנה לחכמים *Miyom shecharav Beis Hamikdash nitlah
nevuah min haneviim venitnah lachachamim*. So from the time the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash* was destroyed, prophecy was taken from the נביאים *neviim*, we
don't have נביאים *neviim* anymore. I mean we certainly didn't have נביאים
*neviim* after the beginning of בית שני *bayis sheini*. Okay, but now
it's given to the חכמים chakhamim *chachamim*. Okay, now, that to be,
you know, that statement by itself could be sort of saying, you
know, not that חכמים chakhamim *chachamim* have נבואה nevuah. *nevuah*, but that
our access to the divine, right, is no longer through נביאים *neviim*,
it is through text and through חכמים chachamim *chachamim* and their role
of interpreting. Right? That is our channel to the divine. It's like
a real... it's a paradigm shift is what it could be saying.
But you know, but you should sort of see it as a
type of a נבואה nevuah. *nevuah*. It's just a נבואה nevuah. *nevuah*
is accessing G-d's word through the, through the, you know, activity of
תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh *torah sheba'al peh*. All right, that's,
I would like to read it that way. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* reads it more literally. No, no, no, the חכמים chachamim *chachamim*
now have נבואה nevuah. *nevuah*. Okay, so let's take a look. This
is obviously playing off of אין אלו אלא דברי נביאות *ein elu
ela divrei nevius*. Okay, so okay, so the חכמים *chachamim* now have
נבואה nevuah, *nevuah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר אמימר *Amar
Ameimar*, אטו חכם chakham לאו נביא הוא *Atu chacham lav navi hu?*
What do you mean? It was taken from the נביאים *neviim* and
given to the חכמים *chachamim*. That suggests that initially the חכמים *chachamim*
didn't, didn't have נבואה nevuah? *nevuah*. Didn't the חכמים *chachamim* always have
נבואה nevuah, *nevuah*? אלא אטו חכם chakham לאו נביא הוא הכי קאמר
*Ela atu chacham lav navi hu hachi ka'amar*. This is what it
means. אף על פי שניטלה מן הנביאים מן החכמים לא ניטלה *Af
al pi shenitlah min neviim min hachachamim lo nitlah*. So even though
it was taken from נביאים *neviim*, it was never taken from the
חכמים *chachamim*. They always had it and they still have it. So
it's really fascinating. The statement which I would say its initial פשט
*pshat* was meant to speak about, about a paradigm shift and about
a change, right, at least that's the way I interpret it, but
now it was reinterpreted in a way that's completely about continuity. Okay?
חכמים *chachamim* always have it, it's nothing new, and they still have
the, the נבואה nevuah, *nevuah* of the, of the past. All right,
so it's a real amazing shift here. אמר אמימר וחכם עדיף מנביא
*Amar Ameimar vechacham adif minavi*. But now we I think get a
pushback, which is like, no, no, no, there's a different type of
an enterprise as being a חכם *chacham* and being a נביא *navi*.
Don't say, oh חכמים *chachamim* still have נבואה nevuah *nevuah*. Being a
חכם *chacham* is better than being a נביא *navi*. Okay, שנאמר ונביא
לבב חכמה *Shene'emar venavi levav chochmah*. And the נביא *navi*, the way
this is reading it, has a heart of wisdom. מי ניתלה במי
*Mi nitlah bemi?* So when you say somebody has this other thing,
so who are, you know, the thing you're attributing is obviously more
important. So הוי אומר קטן ניתלה בגדול *hevei omer katan nitlah begadol*,
the small is hanging himself on the big. So if it says
a נביא *navi* has a heart of wisdom, it means the best
is to be wise, the best is to have a heart of
wisdom. Okay, so this I think gets us back more into the
discontinuity. Okay? That, by the way, is a big phrase used in
rabbinic literature as you can imagine, וחכם עדיף מנביא *chacham adif minavi*.
Okay, which is basically, and it's true, right, you know, the גמרא
*Gemara* comes and says if אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi *Eliyahu HaNavi* were
to come and say that something was הלכה *halachah* we wouldn't listen
to him. That's not the way הלכה *halachah* operates. הלכה *halachah* doesn't
operate through נבואה nevuah *nevuah*. Right? So if you're talking about what
really governs our religious life today in terms of הלכה *halachah*, in
that place it's the role of the חכם *chacham*, that's not the
role of the נביא *navi*, and that's actually the power of that,
of course, is that it's תורה Torah שבעל פה *torah sheba'al peh*.
It's through the human engagement as the, if you see the נביא
*navi* as more just the channel, even though it's a channel that
comes through the prism of somebody's own, you know, sort of intellect
and imagination, but still fundamentally it's the channel whereas this is more
through direct engagement. So חכם *chacham* is עדיף מנביא *adif minavi* both
in terms of his active participation in the process and in terms
of what really governs our lives, and this is the way in
which we access דבר השם *devar Hashem* nowadays. Yes.
I get that, but there also is statements like אליהו Eliyahu הנביא
*Eliyahu HaNavi* will have to resolve it so...
Actually, not. Those statements like תיקו teiku *teiku*, which is read as
that, that's not what the word תיקו *teiku* means. תיקו *teiku* just
means it's a standing question. I know we're told otherwise. But anyway,
all right, let's go on. The גמרא says אליהו הנביא might come
to clarify fact, says the גמרא, but not come to be a
voice. In the ישיבות Yeshivas they say that the word תיקו means
תשבי יתרץ קושיות ואיבעיות. Tishbi Yisaretz Kushyot ve-Ibayot. That's not what it
means! It means תקום! takum! Standing question, unresolved. Okay? The גמרא says
אליהו will resolve factual questions. He will not resolve הלכה questions. He
has no greater standing in הלכה than anybody else. If you want
to prove something in הלכה, you gotta prove it by text. Don't
make reference to divine inspiration, okay, which is exactly the point of
אין אלו דברי נביאות, ein elu divrei neviot, like that's all very
nice, where's your text? Prove it to me. Okay. So this is
like really a strong claim against דעת תורה, Daas Torah, you know?
אמר אביי: Amar Abaye:
תדע! Teda! Now I'll show you that a—now we're going back to
the fact that חכמים still have real נבואה. nevuah. I'll show you
that חכמים still have real נבואה. nevuah דאמר גברא רבה מילתא ומיתאמרא
משמיה דגברא רבה אחרינא כוותיה. De-amar gavra rabba milta u-mitamra mi-shmei de-gavra
rabba achrina kavateih.
Somebody comes up with a brilliant new idea and then you find
out that somebody else, half you know another חכם a hundred miles
away came up with the exact same brilliant idea. So it must
be we were both מכוון mekhuvan to the same like, you know,
divine inspiration or else how did that happen? You know, this, the
best example of this actually happening was, who, who discovered calculus? No,
who discovered calculus? Right. Was it Newton or was it Leibniz? Leibniz,
right? They were in to—no evidence that they had any communication, any
influence, right? And completely
different notations and in—at same time, parallel, they each developed calculus. So,
go figure that out! חכם עדיף מנביא Chakham adif mi-navi or not
adif, he has—they have נבואה. Okay.
So...
and electricity? Edison and somebody else also, I think.
Aha. But were they working because off of the
same—like, if everybody is working to find out to find DNA and
then two people find it at the same time, that's not the
same idea because we're all sort of engaged in the same enterprise.
This was like a real, like, you know, independent field of mathematics.
There was no communication between, between Leibniz and Newton. Oh, maybe. Anyway,
okay. Anyway, okay. This actually has been known to happen. Okay? I
mean, this is a big thing historians are trying—don't understand. How it
happened that ממש mamash at the same time with no communication and
no shared influence, it seems like, you know, Newton and Leibniz both
came up with calculus at the same time. Anyway, okay. תדע דאמר
גברא רבה מילתא ומיתאמרא משמיה דגברא רבה אחרינא כוותיה. Teda de-amar gavra
rabba milta u-mitamra mi-shmei de-gavra rabba achrina kavateih. See? Wow! It looks
like you're just מכוון mekhuvan to something somebody else said. אמר רבא
ומאי קושיא? Amar Rava u-mai kushya? Why is that a question? דלמא
תרוייהו בני חד מזלא נינהו. Dilma tarvaihu bnei chad mazla ninhu. That
doesn't prove נבואה. That just proves they're under the same star and
therefore, you know, it's something more astrological that influences them both to
be מכוון mekhuvan to the same thing.
That's a very Sephardic answer.
So אלא אמר רבא תדע דאמר גברא רבה מילתא ומיתאמרא משמיה דרבי
עקיבא בר יוסף כוותיה. Ela amar Rava teda de-amar gavra rabba milta
u-mitamra mi-shmei de-Rabbi Akiva bar Yosef kavateih.
Somebody came up with an idea and somebody said, oh my God,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said that like a hundred years ago! Now,
obviously, I don't have—I'm not under the same star as רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. So if I could come up with the same brilliant
idea that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva could come up with, it must
be that I have a little bit of נבואה. So the גמרא
says אמר רב אשי ומאי קושיא? Amar Rav Ashi u-mai kushya? Why
is that a—I don't understand how that's נבואה, but okay. ומאי קושיא
דלמא להא מילתא בר מזליה הוא? U-mai kushya dilma le-ha milta bar
mazleih hu? No, maybe you're not under his same star for all
things, but regarding this specific aspect, you share a מזל mazal and
you were able to come up with the same idea.
But the מזל mazal theory is...
what can I tell you? אלא אמר רב אשי תדע דאמר גברא
רבה מילתא ומיתאמרא הלכה למשה מסיני כוותיה. Ela amar Rav Ashi teda
de-amar gavra rabba milta u-mitamra Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai kavateih. You are מכוון
mekhuvan to something that was a tradition from משה מסיני Moshe mi-Sinai
that was not able to be proved by text and nobody would
suggest, God forbid, that you are on the same מזל mazal as
משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. So it must be you had some divine
inspiration in order to come up with it. So the גמרא says
ודלמא כסומא בארובה? Ve-dilma ke-suma be-arubba? Maybe you're just like a blind
man groping around in the darkness, you know, which as the phrase
ארובה arubba literally means a skylight, but it's a euphemism, which basically
means the best English equivalent for this is even a stopped clock
is right twice a day. Okay. So maybe you just got lucky!
That doesn't mean that you were divinely inspired. You came up with
an idea, and by luck, it happened to be something that was
right. Okay? That doesn't mean you have divine inspiration. Okay. So the
גמרא says okay, ולאו טעם יהיב? Ve-lav taam yahiv? One minute! It
wasn't just luck! He gives an explanation for why he came up
with this. So it shows it wasn't just luck. But of course,
the funny thing is, but if you're giving an explanation, then how
does it show it's נבואה? Maybe you just came up with the
right answer. So
it's—it's—it's really fascinating, you know, the shift between נבואה,
logical explanation, and מזל, mazal, right? Like all—on that range of of
different sources of inspi—of how you come up with something. But anyway,
really interesting the payoff between the engagement of תורה Torah שבעל פה
and חכם versus the divine channel of נבואה, you know, and sort
of seeing like which is better and do they have elements of
the other. Yes.
Actually, what what I... What I find, what I really appreciate in
this is I understand that they’re pitted against each other in the
kind of קושיא kushya תירוץ, teirutz, but the fact is most people
discover things with all three elements. Think carefully, you have a moment
of insight and you פאטש potch around through making multiple mistakes all
the time, and scientists have that, all three elements. That’s very nice.
That’s like sort of, that’s like what, what was the Ben Franklin
statement? In, what is it? Discovery or something is like 99% perspiration
and 1% inspiration. Einstein? Really not Franklin?
Franklin said the same thing.
Oh, Franklin said the same thing.
Okay. Alright, very good. Alright, so the גמרא says like this, אמר
רבי יוחנן מיום שחרב בית המקדש ניטלה נבואה מן הנביאים וניתנה לשוטים
ולתינוקות. Amar Rabbi Yochanan mi-yom she-charav Beit HaMikdash nitlah nevuah min ha-nevi'im
u-nitnah le-shotim u-le-tinokot. So rather than saying that the חכמים have it,
no, no, no, we don’t engage in נבואה these days. The חכמים
is rigorous, intellectual,
rational debate. People that might have these
profound moments of insight, of insight or whatever, you know, that’s the
people that are like, that seem like they don’t know anything, and
sometimes they, you know, like from the mouth of babes. It hasn’t
maybe hasn’t been tainted by the other forms of thought. That’s an
interesting, that’s a way of thinking about it, you know, the statement
like from the mouth of babes. What is it? Oh, what’s the
Simon and Garfunkel song? The words of the prophets are written on
the subway walls, right? That’s where we get our נבואה these days
from the outcast of society, maybe, or those ignored by society. Maybe
they have, oh I’m sorry, I’m just free associating now. But do
you remember, people know Men in Black, the scene where all the
news comes, all the true news comes from the tabloids. It’s those
people that sound crazy that are at the edge of society, they’re
the ones that have the נבואה. Okay, וניתנה לשוטים ולתינוקות. u-nitnah le-shotim
u-le-tinokot. Okay, לשוטים le-shotim מאי היא?
mai hi? Where’s the example of שוטים?
shotim? כי הא דמר בר רב אשי דהוה קאי בריסתקא דמחוזא. Ki
ha de-Mar bar Rav Ashi de-hava kai be-ristaka de-Mechuza. He was
standing in like the marketplace or the main thoroughfare of מחוזא. Mechuza.
שמעי לההוא שוטה, Shamei le-hahu shoteh, he heard a certain שוטה. shoteh.
A שוטה shoteh is like somebody who is normally somebody like is
a little like mentally unwell, so it seems like a mental illness
or schizophrenic sometimes it sounds like it’s describing, but somebody clearly who
is, you know, on the outskirts of society. דקאמר, De-ka-amar, ריש מתיבתא
דמליך במתא מחסיא טביומי חתים. reish metivta de-mali'akh be-matta Mechasiya Tivyomei khatim.
The next ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, the person who's going to be
the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, טביומי Tivyomei signs his name טביומי. Tivyomei.
This is just סתם, stam, he said this randomly. אמר, so רב
אשי Rav Ashi said, מאן חתים טביומי ברבנן? Man khatim Tivyomei berabbanan?
Wait a minute, who among the rabbis signs their names טביומי? Tivyomei?
אנא, Ana, that would be me. שמע מינה לדידי קאי לשעתא, Shema
mina le-didi kai le-sha'ata, so if that’s what this person is saying,
it must be there’s an element of נבואה in this, so it
must be now is my opportunity. Okay, now is my time. קם
אתא, Kam ata, so he got up, he went. He was going
to the ישיבה. yeshiva. אדאתי אינו רבנן לאוקמי לרב אחא מדפתי ברישא.
Ad de-atei innu rabbanan le-okmei le-Rav Akha mi-Difti be-reisha.
Obviously there was a changing of the guards, they were waiting, you
know it was the time they were working to appoint somebody. So
there was a vacant seat there. So the rabbis had already taken
a vote and they did not vote to have רב אשי Rav
Ashi as the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, they had voted to have
רב אחא מדפתי Rav Akha mi-Difti as the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva.
כיון דשמעי דאתא, Keivan de-shami de-ata, but then they heard that רב
אשי Rav Ashi was coming, מר בר רב אשי, Mar bar Rav
Ashi, excuse me, thank you, מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav
Ashi was coming. שדרו זוגא דרבנן לגביה למימלך ביה. Shadaru zuga de-rabbanan
lagabei le-imlukhi bei. Oh, מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi
is coming, we better get his opinion who he thinks should be
the right ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. So they sent two rabbis. עכביה,
Akvei, so he held them over, he didn’t let them go back.
Okay, he had them stay with him. הדר שדרו זוגא דרבנן אחרינא.
Hadar shadaru zuga de-rabbanan achrina. So then they sent another pair of
rabbis, they weren’t getting a response. עכביה, Akvei, he held them back
לגביה. lagabei. עד דמלו בי עשרה, Ad de-malo be-asara, until there were
ten. He had sent five groups of rabbis and he had, so
now he had ten rabbis with him. כיון דמלו בי עשרה, Keivan
de-malo be-asara, now that there were ten rabbis, פתח הוא ותנא ודרש.
patach hu ve-tana ve-darash. He got up and he taught and he
explicated. לפי שאין פותחין בכלה פחות מעשרה. Lefi she-ein potkhin be-khallah pakhut
me-asara. You don’t open a rabbinic discourse, כלה kallah sometimes means the
discourse before the חגים, chaggim, but it could also mean a rabbinic
discourse, with fewer than ten people. So he started giving like a
שיעור, shiur, okay? Who do you don’t give a שיעור shiur unless
you’re the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, alright? So therefore he effectively, you
know, used the opportunity to make himself the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva,
and then it was already a done deal. קרי רב אחא אנפשיה.
Kari Rav Akha anafshei. Now remember, רב אחא Rav Akha was the
guy who they had voted on, and now it basically had gotten
stolen from him. So רב אחא Rav Akha said about himself, אנפשיה:
anafshei: כל דמריעין לו לא במהרה מטיבין לו וכל דמטיבין לו לא
במהרה מריעין לו. kol de-mari'in lo lo bimherah metivin lo ve-khol de-metivin
lo lo bimherah mari'in lo. Anybody who you know it, they do,
you know that bad happens to him, they don’t quickly have good
things happen to them, or it’s from heaven it’s decreed, and anybody
that has good happen to him, it won’t quickly have bad things,
which basically means
like. Like here this bad fortune fell me and here was my
chance and it was squandered and it's not going to be easy
to recover this opportunity. Like this was my chance and I blew
it or I didn't blow it, it got taken from me and
it's probably unrealistic to hope that I will quickly get that opportunity
to be ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva again. Now תוספות Tosafot has a
very sad conclusion to this. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot כל
המריעין לו לא במהרה מטיבין לו, kol hamarian lo lo bimehair metivin
lo, ובשאילתא מרובה דקאמר רב אחא גופיה, uv'shaili mruva d'ka'amar Rav Acha
gufei, the same רב אחא Rav Acha says לעולם אין מטיבין לו.
l'olam ein metivin lo. Not that after something bad happened it won't
quickly turn around, but it'll never turn around. So which is it?
Will it not quickly turn around or never turn around? So תוספות
says איכא למימר דמתחילה אמר לא במהרה מטיבין לו ika l'meimar d'mitechila
amar lo bimehair metivin lo שהיה מצפה שיחזירו לו גדולתו. shehaya metzapeh
sheyachaziru lo gedulato. So it won't quickly turn around, maybe I'll have
to wait another twenty years for my chance. וכשראה שלא החזירו שוב
אמר שוב אמר לעולם אין מטיבין לו. u'keshera'ah shelo hechiziru shuv amar
shuv amar l'olam ein metivin lo. But then after twenty years he
still wasn't getting it, he said that's it, it's never going to
happen. Okay, that's very sad. But I also want to say in
terms of the story, how much was this a דברי נבואה? divrei
nevuah? Cause at the end מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav
Ashi really manipulated the whole thing. Right? But the דברי נבואה divrei
nevuah was had he not heard from this person saying it, he
wouldn't have started heading to מחוזא. Mechuza. And only because the rabbis
heard he was heading to מחוזא Mechuza did they consult with him.
But at the end of the day it was all because of
choices he made, but the initial choice was because of this inspiration.
So it's sort of like self-fulfilling prophecy, right? You can if you
hear this prophecy and you act on it as prophecy, maybe it
will become prophecy.
Like the joke the guy who's drowning, right, and a boat goes
by and throws him a thing.
Right,
he was very active in making it into a words of prophecy.
But it did inspire him, it was the catalyst.
Yes, just like in תנ"ך Tanakh where there's prophecy and they go
to
make sure that it happens. Right, right, yes.
It's just amazing that it's such a modern trope, both the self-fulfilling
prophecy idea, the question of how much is prophecy really prophecy and
how much is it just controlling our actions, and also the idea
of like the mentally ill being prophets is also I think a
common... if you look at movies, right, right.
It's always those people that are looking crazy that they really have
some real truth in them.
Yeah, like I don't know if it's like a desire to explain
mental illness or a desire to...
I don't know, right, right, yes, absolutely, yep. Okay, so now we
have children, okay? So or small girls actually, I think if the
word תינוקות tinokot and I mean I don't know if that's limited
to girls but the story here is with girls. What? תינוקת. tinoket.
תינוקת? tinoket? But in the first
it said בשיעת תינוקות. bish'at tinokot. תינוקות. tinokot. The first was בשיעת
תינוקות. bish'at tinokot. If it was תינוקת tinoket it certainly would be
girls. תינוקות tinokot could be... it's the feminine noun so it could
mean children.
But the example is one of a תינוקת. tinoket. So let's take
a look. Okay, so the גמרא says like this. Okay, where were
we? Okay, now תינוקת, tinoket, now we've turned so now we've used
it in the singular, right? And the example here is of about
a young girl. מאי היא? Mai hi? כי הא דבת רב חסדא,
Ki had'bat Rav Chisda, the daughter of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, הוה
יתבה בכנפי דאבוה. hava yatva b'chanei d'avuha. So she was sitting there
in the cloak of her father, like on her father's lap or
whatever. והוה יתבי קמי דרבא, V'hava yatvi kamei d'Rava, קמי רבא ורמי
בר חמא. kamei Rava v'Rami bar Chama. רבא Rava and רמי בר
חמא Rami bar Chama
were both sitting in front of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, they were
learning תורה or whatever, his young daughter was on his lap. אמר
לה, Amar lah, so he turned to his daughter and said, you
know, I got these two students, big תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, מאן
מינייהו בעית, Man minaihu ba'yit,
which one do you think you'd like to marry? אמר, she said,
אמר ליה תרוייהו, amar lei tarvaihu, I'll take both of them. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said, ואני בתרא, v'ani batra, I'll
be the second. So, why did he say he'll be the second?
Cause why did he want to be the last? Because what happens
to the first? He dies. Right. So anyway, and lo and behold
that happened. First she married רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama and
then רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama died and then she married
רבא. Rava. Of course, here you're talking about choices that people are
making, right? So it's like you plant the seed, right? And she
shows an interest and they show interest or whatever, anyway, and anyway,
it's a ראש ישיבה's Rosh Yeshiva daughter, so okay.
עגנון Agnon also has this daughter
that plays off of this? Right. אמר רב דימי מן חיפא. Amar
Rav Dimi min Haifa. Now because we quoted רב דימי מן חיפא
Rav Dimi min Haifa before about prophecy being taken from the prophets
and given to the sages, it's another statement of his. Yes.
What about the essence of prophecy being to correction rather than, you
know, like prophecy coming because something needs to change...
this is just purely like access to the future type of a
thing. That's a good point, it's not the prophecy of getting people
to... right, exactly, that's a very good point too. Tomorrow's futures. Yeah,
yeah, it's a good point. אמר רב דימי מן חיפא, Amar Rav
Dimi min Haifa, קודם שיאכל אדם. kodem she-yochal adam.
Now similarly רב דימי מן חיפא Rav Dimi min Haifa says, קודם
שיאכל אדם וישתה יש לו שתי לבבות. kodem she-yochal adam v'yishteh yesh
lo shtei levavot. This has nothing to do with what came before,
but it's the same person saying it. Okay, before a person eats
he has... two hearts, meaning, you know, you can't try to get
somebody who's hungry to focus on something because part of their mind
is always thinking about their hunger. All right, so before they eat,
they're just too distracted. ואחר שאוכל ושותה אין לו אלא לב אחד:
ve-achar she-ochal ve-shoteh ein lo ela lev echad: after he eats and
drinks and he's sated, then he only has, then he can totally
focus, he has one heart. שנאמר איש נבוב ילבב. shene'emar ish navov
yilavev.
Okay,
a person נבוב, navov, which we'll treat as like empty, okay, he
has like a cavity, he will have ילבב, yilavev, the double ב,
bet, ילבב yilavev is two hearts. וכתיב נבוב לוחות u-ketiv nivuv luchot
ומתרגמינן חליל לוחין u-metargeminan chalil luchin
like the carved out or the cavity, you know, of the of
the of the tablets, and therefore it's like your, you know, your
stomach is hollow and therefore ילבב yilavev you've got two hearts. אמר
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע: Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua: הרגיל
ביין אפילו לבו אטום כבתולה יין מפקחו, ha-ragil be-yayin afillu libbo atum
ke-vetulah yayin mefakcho,
very interesting imagery here. A person who is, who has a lot,
who is accustomed to drinking wine, even if his heart is stopped
up like a virgin, the wine will open it up. שנאמר ותירוש
ינובב בתולות. shene'emar ve-tirosh yenovev betulot. So again, ינובב yenovev here playing
off of the נבוב לוחות, nivuv luchot, hollow, open, and so on,
and the בתולות, betulot, so therefore it opens it up. Very, of
course, the whole imagery of wine and virgin and whatever, I mean,
the גמרא in the beginning of כתובות, Ketubot, okay, we're going to
move on. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע: Amar Rav Huna brei
de-Rav Yehoshua: פשיטא. peshita.
Now, okay, now we're getting back to dividing a plot of land,
okay. פשיטא חלק בכור וחלק פשוט יהבינן ליה אחד מצרא. peshita chelek
bechor ve-chelek pashut yavinan leh achad metzra.
Now
we're going to divide a plot of land, okay, we've either agreed
to it or you've forced the division because it's big enough, and
they're brothers, Reuven and Shimon. Now Reuven is the בכור bechor so
he
gets, he gets two pieces of the division, it's an ancestral plot
that they're dividing, okay. So Reuven, if, so imagine that you had,
I don't know, let's say you've got like, you know, I don't
know, you had all those divisions, and Reuven is going to get
two of them, okay. So Reuven is entitled to get two that
are side-by-side, okay, 'cause obviously you want one big plot of land
rather than two separate plots of land, okay. So that פשיטא, peshita,
it's obvious to us, חלק בכור וחלק פשוט, chelek bechor ve-chelek pashut,
his, the extra portion he gets as being a בכור, bechor, and
the base portion he gets as a פשוט pashut as a normal
son, יהבינן ליה אחד מצרא, yavinan leh achad metzra, we give him
on one shared boundary. Right, on one boundary.
So it could, it could be
this, you know, or whatever, I mean, you'll figure that out, but
he's entitled to have two of them together. Okay. יבם מה? Yavam
mah?
Now, how about if somebody, brother dies and he performs יבום yibum
with his sister-in-law,
and therefore he's entitled, now the father dies, to his brother's portion,
so he has his portion and his brother's portion together
and, you know, he wants to get them together, but the other
brothers don't want to give it to them together. They're either they
סתם stam want their portion he wants, or maybe more, they want
to get paid to give him that accommodation. Sure, we'll give it
to you together, how much will you pay us for that? Okay.
So can he demand the right to get them together, his portion
plus his brother's portion because he's the יבם? Yavam? Okay. יבם מה?
Yavam mah? אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: היא היא, hi hi, same, same
point, he's entitled to them together. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, בכור קרא
רחמנא bechor kara rachmana 'cause the תורה calls him בכור. bechor. Now,
it really doesn't call him בכור, bechor, it says והיה הבכור אשר
תלד יקום על שם אביו המת, ve-hayah ha-bechor asher teled yakum al
shem aviv ha-met, אחיו המת. achiv ha-met. Is it אחיו? achiv? אחיו
המת. achiv ha-met. Okay.
Anyway, the בכור bechor that will be born, but the גמרא in
its דרשה drasha reads והיה הבכור, ve-hayah ha-bechor, the one who does
the יבום yibum is like a בכור bechor and he gets a
second portion. He has the דין din of a בכור, bechor, so
the same way a בכור bechor second portion comes together with his
base one, the extra portion he gets for because of his brother
comes together with the one he had for himself. והיה הבכור. ve-hayah
ha-bechor. Okay. So that's what Abaye says, you get them together. רבא
אמר: Rava amar: אמר קרא והיה הבכור, amar kra ve-hayah ha-bechor, הויה
כבכור ואין חלוקתו כבכור. havayah k-bechor ve-ein chalukato k-bechor. He's like a
בכור bechor in terms of his identity, but he does not get
to divide the property as a בכור. bechor. Okay. Now, now another
story. ההוא דזבן ארעא אמצרא דבי נשא. Hahu d-zaven ara a-metzra de-bei
nasha. Somebody bought a plot of land on a boundary of, now
בי נשא bei nasha is an interesting phrase because normally it means
like, like could, it could mean a woman's house. Okay. And what
it's often or it means a father-in-law's house. If somebody in their
כתובה ketubah is getting married and the father has is not alive
and it's been living in their mother's household, the girl, the girl,
the woman, and you know where you say that she's bringing property,
you normally say מבי אבוה. mi-bei avuha. So if if the father
is not alive, you would write the property that she brought מבי
נשא. mi-bei nasha. Okay. Now what does that mean? It could mean
the woman's home because like it's the mother's home now, it's not
the, some say it means נשי neshi means what? It means in
Aramaic to forget because like you have sort of forgotten the father,
which is the primary identity. Anyway, so here it could mean, it
would mean, you know, תוספות suggest. Says that it means the father-in-laws.
So basically here's the story, okay? Here is יעקב Yaakov and he
has a daughter דינה, Dinah, okay? And then now somebody else, I
don't know, whatever, ברק Barak here is married to דינה. Dinah. Okay?
So ברק Barak and he has other daughters as well. He has
other— okay, that's not working biblically anymore. Okay, whatever. Okay. Anyway, so
ברק Barak is married to one of his daughters and he buys
a plot of land right here. And it's a מצר by the
boundary of בי נשא, Bei Nasha, of the plot of land owned
by his father-in-law, or you know, again, this word like the women
because it's going to be the women who are going to divide
it, anyway owned by his father-in-law. Then יעקב Yaakov dies. So now,
and לאה Leah has already died. And now יעקב Yaakov dies. So
he or whatever, יעקב Yaakov dies, whatever, I figured it out. Anyway,
he's entitled to לאה's Leah portion, okay, because he inherits לאה. Leah.
So he wants his portion that his wife gets, you know, being
part of these daughters, to be next to his plot of land,
right? He wants it on the plot of land. Okay. So let's
take a look. כי קא
פלגו, Ki ka palgu, when the daughters divided, אמרי פלגו לי אמצראי,
Amrei palgu li amitzrai, I would like my plot of my you
know my wife's plot of land, I want it on my border.
So אמר רבא כגון זה כופין על מדת סדום. Amar Rava kigone
zeh kofin al middat Sdom. So this you force people, מדת סדום
Middat Sdom is the guy who says שלי שלי ושלך שלך, sheli
sheli veshelcha shelcha, which means like, you know, I don't owe you
anything, I don't have to do anything for you, even if it
costs me nothing, you, you know, I have no obligation to you.
So כופין על מדת סדום Kofin al middat Sdom means it's a
case of like זה נהנה וזה לא חסר, zeh neheneh vezeh lo
chaser, that's essentially the point, you're not going to lose anything from
this, right? So why not? Like if all these plots are equal,
why not do the guy the favor and give him the plot
that makes life better for him? Of course the answer could be
because I don't have to do him the favor and I could
actually get him to pay for me to do him the favor,
so why should I just סתם stam do him the favor? Okay,
so that's the question. When is it really considered like it doesn't
cost me anything? I'm foregoing an opportunity to maybe make some money.
Why should I give him that accommodation if I could charge for
it? So let's take a look. So it says, מתיב ליה רב
יוסף, Masiv leh Rav Yosef, so that's what רב יוסף Rav Yosef.
says back. אמרי ליה אחא Amri leh acha or some
have אח אחוותא ach achvata whatever, the sisters or the brothers, depending
on how you understand the story, can say to him, מעלינן ליה
עילויא כנכסי דבר מריון. Maalinen leh illuya kinichsei debar Maryon. Sure, you
want that plot of land? Pay us a huge amount of money
like נכסי דבר מריון, nichsei debar Maryon, these rich people, okay? Sure,
we'll give you that plot of land after we've doubled the price
of it, okay? So basically you are asking them to forego an
opportunity so to make some money to give him that accommodation, they
have no obligation to do so.
עילויא Illuya means like what עולה? oleh?
Yeah, exactly. We'll raise the price. הלכתא כרב יוסף, Hilchasa keRav Yosef,
we rule like רב יוסף. Let's just read one or two more
lines. תרי ארעתא אמתרי, Trei arasa amtrei, you know, maybe not, it's
already 8:30. Okay, so we're going to continue with this discussion tomorrow
about when you divide a plot of land, if somebody wants an
accommodation that doesn't cost you any loss, but maybe you have a
right to be paid to give him that accommodation, is that a
case of כופין על מדת סדום kofin al middat Sdom or not?
So we will continue with this issue tomorrow. All right. יישר כח.
Yasher koach.